<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Managing with AI</title>
<link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/</link>
<atom:link href="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Managing with Data: Analytics and Artificial Intelligence</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>On Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert W. Walker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-15-2026/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What is a model?</p>
<p>Our reading for today defines models in science. This is a hard read but it is the only reading for the week.</p>
<p><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/">Models in Science from the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</a></p>
<p>We will pay extra attention to sections 1, 3, and 5.2.</p>
<p>The class plan:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>What is a model?</li>
<li>Sharing insights from unfamiliar models supplied by Gemini.</li>
<li>Models in business?</li>
</ol>
<p>Your assignment for this time:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Do the reading.</li>
<li>Collect at least three questions and the answers provided by Google Gemini about references in the reading that were unfamiliar. If you did not run across at least three unfamiliar references, you need a more advanced course.</li>
</ol>
<section id="my-homework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-homework">My Homework</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/107KPF3BsF2NiAPnoKgC0gisqlqZKsaSJuenrjHQYOpg/edit?usp=sharing">The Lorenz Model</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/138wuCj5-0PanIFdNf2MVjas4ZI3fT_j8aymWNiuLFa8/edit?usp=sharing">The double helix model of DNA</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1RB5tjcRtYaalPQL_pQU_m1WgmZ9EIKGksar5GlkZ7Dk/edit?usp=sharing">What is ontology?</a></p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./ontology.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Imagine that"><img src="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-15-2026/ontology.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Imagine that"></a></p>
<figcaption>Imagine that</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="an-example" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-example">An Example</h2>
<p>Source: <a href="https://x.com/pablohernandezb/status/2010762183752536193?s=46">x.com</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./ven-map.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Map of Venezuela"><img src="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-15-2026/ven-map.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Map of Venezuela"></a></p>
<figcaption>Map of Venezuela</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="for-next-class" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-next-class">For Next Class:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Reading: Chapter 1: Open Introduction to Statistics: <em>(On Canvas &gt; Files &gt; OpenIntroStatistics)</em>.<br>
</li>
<li>Deliverable: An In-class exercise [Assignment 2] and pending Assignment 1</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="my-assignment-1" class="level1">
<h1>My Assignment 1</h1>
<section id="prompt-what-is-the-lorenz-model-of-climate-extremes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prompt-what-is-the-lorenz-model-of-climate-extremes">Prompt: What is the Lorenz model of climate extremes?</h2>
<p>The Lorenz model is a simplified mathematical model used to describe atmospheric convection.1 It is one of the most famous systems in physics because it was the first to demonstrate chaotic behavior—the phenomenon where deterministic systems behave unpredictably due to extreme sensitivity to initial conditions.2</p>
<p>This model is responsible for the modern understanding that long-term weather forecasting is fundamentally impossible, a concept popularized as the “Butterfly Effect.”3</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Origin: A Happy Accident In 1963, MIT meteorologist Edward Lorenz was using a computer to simulate weather patterns.4 He was running a code based on twelve equations that modeled the way air moves when it is heated from below and cooled from above.5</li>
</ol>
<p>One day, he wanted to repeat a simulation he had run previously.6 To save time, he started the run from the middle, typing in numbers from a previous printout. The printout displayed numbers to 3 decimal places (e.g., 0.506), but the computer calculated internally to 6 decimal places (e.g., 0.506127).7</p>
<p>Lorenz assumed this tiny difference (one part in a thousand) would have no meaningful effect. Instead, he found that the new simulation quickly diverged completely from the original, looking like a totally different weather system.8 This led him to publish his landmark paper, “Deterministic Nonperiodic Flow,” which founded the field of Chaos Theory.9</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The Equations Lorenz simplified his original twelve equations down to just three coupled, non-linear ordinary differential equations.10</li>
</ol>
<p>While they were derived from the complex Navier-Stokes equations (which describe fluid motion), Lorenz reduced them to a “toy model” representing a single 2D slice of atmosphere behaving like a convection roll (gas rising and falling in a loop). The equations are:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%20%5Cfrac%7Bdx%7D%7Bdt%7D%20&amp;=%20%5Csigma%20(y%20-%20x)%20%5C%5C%20%5Cfrac%7Bdy%7D%7Bdt%7D%20&amp;=%20x%20(%5Crho%20-%20z)%20-%20y%20%5C%5C%20%5Cfrac%7Bdz%7D%7Bdt%7D%20&amp;=%20x%20y%20-%20%5Cbeta%20z%20%5Cend%7Baligned%7D"></p>
<p>The Variables (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x,%20y,%20z">) These do not represent coordinates in real space (like latitude/longitude). They represent the state of the fluid at any given moment: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x">: The intensity of convection.11 (How fast is the convective roll spinning?)</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y">: The horizontal temperature difference between the ascending (warm) and descending (cool) currents.12</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z">: The vertical temperature distortion.13 (How much the temperature profile deviates from a linear decrease with height).14</p>
<p>The Parameters (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma,%20%5Crho,%20%5Cbeta">) These are constants that determine the physical properties of the “atmosphere”:15</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"> (Sigma): The Prandtl number (viscosity relative to thermal conductivity).16</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Crho"> (Rho): The Rayleigh number (the temperature difference between the hot ground and the cool sky).17 This is the “control knob”—if you turn it up high enough, the system becomes chaotic.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta"> (Beta): A geometric factor related to the size of the convection roll. Lorenz found the famous chaotic behavior using the specific values: 18<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma%20=%2010">, 19<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta%20=%208/3">, and 20<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Crho%20=%2028">.21</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The Butterfly Effect &amp; The Attractor</li>
</ol>
<p>If you plot the values of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z"> over time in 3D space, the line traces out a shape that looks remarkably like a butterfly. This shape is known as the Lorenz Attractor.22 It has two “wings” (lobes):23</p>
<p>Left Wing: The fluid is rotating in one direction. Right Wing: The fluid reverses and rotates in the opposite direction. The Chaos: The system orbits one wing for a while, then suddenly switches to the other.24 There is no pattern to when it switches. You cannot predict when the flip will happen.</p>
<p>This visualization illustrates the Butterfly Effect: two points on the attractor that are infinitesimally close together (representing two weather systems that are almost identical) will eventually end up on opposite wings of the attractor (completely different weather).25</p>
<p>Summary of Significance Weather Prediction: The model proved that because we cannot measure the current state of the atmosphere with infinite precision (infinite decimal places), we cannot predict the weather beyond a certain timeframe (roughly two weeks). Deterministic Chaos: It proved that a system can be completely deterministic (follows rigid equations) but still behave randomly.26</p>
<p>Fractals: The “Strange Attractor” is a fractal; it has infinite detail and a fractional dimension (roughly 2.06 dimensions).27</p>
<p>Would you like me to generate a Python script to solve these equations so you can see the butterfly attractor evolve yourself?</p>
</section>
<section id="prompt-what-is-the-double-helix-model-of-dna" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prompt-what-is-the-double-helix-model-of-dna">Prompt: What is the double helix model of DNA?</h2>
<p>The double helix model is the description of the three-dimensional structure of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid).1 It depicts DNA not as a flat ladder, but as two long strands twisted around each other like a spiral staircase.2</p>
<p>This model was first published in 1953 and is considered one of the most significant discoveries in the history of biology because it revealed how genetic information is stored and copied.3</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Structure: A Twisted Ladder4 If you imagine a ladder twisted into a spiral, the double helix has two main parts: The Backbone (The Rails): The outside of the helix is formed by alternating sugar (deoxyribose) and phosphate molecules.5 This “sugar-phosphate backbone” provides the structural framework.</li>
</ol>
<p>The Base Pairs (The Rungs): Inside the helix, connecting the two backbones, are pairs of nitrogenous bases.6 These bases hold the two strands together using hydrogen bonds.7</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Key Rules of the Model The double helix is highly specific in how it is built. Three chemical rules are essential to its function: Complementary Base Pairing: The “rungs” are not random.8 A base on one strand always pairs with a specific partner on the other strand:9</li>
</ol>
<p>Adenine (A) always pairs with Thymine (T).10</p>
<p>Cytosine (C) always pairs with Guanine (G).11</p>
<p>Why this matters: This means if you know the sequence of one strand (e.g., A-C-T-G), you automatically know the sequence of the other (T-G-A-C).12 This is the secret to how DNA copies itself.</p>
<p>Antiparallel Strands: The two strands run in opposite directions.13 Chemical direction is measured from the 14<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?5'"> (five-prime) end to the 15<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?3'"> (three-prime) end.16 In the double helix, one strand runs 17<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?5'%20%5Cto%203'"> while the other runs 18<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?3'%20%5Cto%205'">.19</p>
<p>Right-Handed Twist: In nature (specifically B-DNA, the most common form), the helix twists to the right, completing a full turn roughly every 10.5 base pairs.20</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The Discovery The discovery of the double helix is a famous (and controversial) story of scientific competition: Watson &amp; Crick: James Watson and Francis Crick are credited with proposing the model in 1953.21 They built physical models (using cardboard and metal plates) to fit the chemical pieces together.22 +1</li>
</ol>
<p>Rosalind Franklin: Her work was crucial but often overlooked at the time.23 She was an expert in X-ray crystallography and captured Photo 51, a famous X-ray image that clearly showed the “X” pattern characteristic of a helix.24 Watson used this data (shown to him without her permission by Maurice Wilkins) to confirm the helical structure.25 +2</p>
<p>The Nobel Prize: In 1962, Watson, Crick, and Wilkins were awarded the Nobel Prize.26 Franklin had passed away four years earlier and was not eligible for the posthumous award, though modern science recognizes her as a co-discoverer.</p>
<p>Summary of Components Component Description Nucleotide</p>
<p>The basic building block, consisting of one sugar, one phosphate, and one base. Hydrogen Bonds Weak bonds that hold the A-T and C-G base pairs together (like a zipper). Sugar-Phosphate The structural “rails” that protect the genetic code inside.</p>
<p>Would you like me to explain how the Double Helix “unzips” to replicate itself?</p>
</section>
<section id="prompt-what-is-ontology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prompt-what-is-ontology">Prompt: What is ontology?</h2>
<p>Ontology is, at its core, the study of what exists and how things are related.1</p>
<p>Depending on whether you are talking to a philosopher or a computer scientist, the definition shifts from abstract reality to practical data structures.2</p>
<p>Here is the breakdown of the two main perspectives: 1. In Philosophy (The Origin)3 In philosophy, ontology is the “study of being.”4 It is a branch of metaphysics that asks deep questions about the nature of reality.5</p>
<p>The Goal: To discover the fundamental categories of existence.6</p>
<p>Key Questions: What does it mean “to exist”? Do abstract ideas (like the number 7 or “justice”) exist in the same way a rock exists? Example: A philosopher might analyze if “holes” are real things, or if they are just the absence of something else. 2. In Computer Science (The Application) In computer science (specifically AI and Information Science), an ontology is a formal blueprint used to model knowledge.7 It is a specific way of organizing data so that computers can “understand” it.8</p>
<p>Instead of asking “what is reality,” a computational ontology declares: “For this specific system, these are the only things that exist, and here is how they connect.” The Goal: To help software share data, reason about information, and avoid confusion.9</p>
<p>The “Triples” Structure: Most computational ontologies are built on three main components: Classes (The Nouns): The categories of things (e.g., Patient, Doctor, Drug).10</p>
<p>Attributes (The Adjectives): The properties of those things (e.g., Name, Dosage, Blood Type).11</p>
<p>Relationships (The Verbs): How they interact (e.g., Doctor prescribes Drug). Summary Comparison Feature Philosophical Ontology Computational Ontology Focus The nature of reality. The structure of a specific domain’s data. Goal Truth and wisdom. Interoperability (systems talking to each other). Output Theories and essays. Knowledge Graphs, code (OWL/RDF), databases. Example “Is the mind separate from the body?” “A Smartphone is-a Device.”</p>
<p>Why is this important right now? You likely interact with ontologies every day without realizing it: Google Search: When you search for “Jaguar,” Google uses an ontology to figure out if you mean the animal, the car, or the football team based on the other words in your query. Healthcare: Ontologies allow different hospitals to share records. One system might say “Heart Attack” and another “Myocardial Infarction,” but the ontology links them as the exact same concept. Next Step Would you like me to show you a text-based example of what a simple ontology looks like for a common domain, like a Library or a Smart Home?</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-15-2026/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-15-2026/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="73" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Formatting a Gemini Response</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert W. Walker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Gemini-Formatting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level1">
<h1>TL;DR</h1>
<p>Gemini is powerful, and a few tidbits help a great deal. I use <code>markdown</code> formatting for text inputs and Gemini is well versed in this. My prompts now use <code>please format responses in markdown and include links to the noted sources</code>.</p>
</section>
<section id="getting-formatted-responses-from-gemini" class="level1">
<h1>Getting Formatted Responses from Gemini</h1>
<p>Our homework for tomorrow is to utilize Gemini to assist us in reading the Stanford entry on models. I provided three examples, let me focus on the <strong>ontology</strong> response. First, let me replay the interaction noting that the ultimate concern is formatting.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-empty-content callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Prompt: What is ontology?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">

</div>
</div>
<p>Ontology is, at its core, the study of what exists and how things are related.1</p>
<p>Depending on whether you are talking to a philosopher or a computer scientist, the definition shifts from abstract reality to practical data structures.2</p>
<p>Here is the breakdown of the two main perspectives: 1. In Philosophy (The Origin)3 In philosophy, ontology is the “study of being.”4 It is a branch of metaphysics that asks deep questions about the nature of reality.5</p>
<p>The Goal: To discover the fundamental categories of existence.6</p>
<p>Key Questions: What does it mean “to exist”? Do abstract ideas (like the number 7 or “justice”) exist in the same way a rock exists? Example: A philosopher might analyze if “holes” are real things, or if they are just the absence of something else. 2. In Computer Science (The Application) In computer science (specifically AI and Information Science), an ontology is a formal blueprint used to model knowledge.7 It is a specific way of organizing data so that computers can “understand” it.8</p>
<p>Instead of asking “what is reality,” a computational ontology declares: “For this specific system, these are the only things that exist, and here is how they connect.” The Goal: To help software share data, reason about information, and avoid confusion.9</p>
<p>The “Triples” Structure: Most computational ontologies are built on three main components: Classes (The Nouns): The categories of things (e.g., Patient, Doctor, Drug).10</p>
<p>Attributes (The Adjectives): The properties of those things (e.g., Name, Dosage, Blood Type).11</p>
<p>Relationships (The Verbs): How they interact (e.g., Doctor prescribes Drug). Summary Comparison Feature Philosophical Ontology Computational Ontology Focus The nature of reality. The structure of a specific domain’s data. Goal Truth and wisdom. Interoperability (systems talking to each other). Output Theories and essays. Knowledge Graphs, code (OWL/RDF), databases. Example “Is the mind separate from the body?” “A Smartphone is-a Device.”</p>
<p>Why is this important right now? You likely interact with ontologies every day without realizing it: Google Search: When you search for “Jaguar,” Google uses an ontology to figure out if you mean the animal, the car, or the football team based on the other words in your query. Healthcare: Ontologies allow different hospitals to share records. One system might say “Heart Attack” and another “Myocardial Infarction,” but the ontology links them as the exact same concept. Next Step Would you like me to show you a text-based example of what a simple ontology looks like for a common domain, like a Library or a Smart Home?</p>
<section id="commentary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="commentary">Commentary</h2>
<p>The content is excellent. The formatting is not. And the <code>Docs</code> version is no better.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./Gemini-Doc.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Gemini output"><img src="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Gemini-Formatting/Gemini-Doc.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Gemini output"></a></p>
<figcaption>Gemini output</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The notes have no content. It looks fine but it is not complete. Let me prompt again and see if I can get something to work with.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-second-response" class="level1">
<h1>The Second Response</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Prompt: What is ontology?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This is a great response. When it is exported to google docs, the footnotes with citations are lost. Could you instead respond with harder to read markdown code so that the citations and notes are present in the response in a format that is easy to re-render?</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Ontology</strong> is, at its core, the study of <strong>what exists</strong> and <strong>how things are related</strong>.</p>
<p>Depending on whether you are talking to a philosopher or a computer scientist, the definition shifts from abstract reality to practical data structures.</p>
<p>Here is the breakdown of the two main perspectives:</p>
<section id="in-philosophy-the-origin" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-philosophy-the-origin">1. In Philosophy (The Origin)</h3>
<p>In philosophy, ontology is the “study of being.” It is a branch of metaphysics that asks deep questions about the nature of reality. * <strong>The Goal:</strong> To discover the fundamental categories of existence. * <strong>Key Questions:</strong> What does it mean “to exist”? Do abstract ideas (like the number 7 or “justice”) exist in the same way a rock exists? * <strong>Example:</strong> A philosopher might analyze if “holes” are real things, or if they are just the absence of something else.</p>
</section>
<section id="in-computer-science-the-application" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-computer-science-the-application">2. In Computer Science (The Application)</h3>
<p>In computer science (specifically AI and Information Science), an ontology is a <strong>formal blueprint</strong> used to model knowledge. It is a specific way of organizing data so that computers can “understand” it.</p>
<p>Instead of asking “what is reality,” a computational ontology declares: <em>“For this specific system, these are the only things that exist, and here is how they connect.”</em></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Goal:</strong> To help software share data, reason about information, and avoid confusion.</li>
<li><strong>The “Triples” Structure:</strong> Most computational ontologies are built on three main components:
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Classes (The Nouns):</strong> The categories of things (e.g., <code>Patient</code>, <code>Doctor</code>, <code>Drug</code>).</li>
<li><strong>Attributes (The Adjectives):</strong> The properties of those things (e.g., <code>Name</code>, <code>Dosage</code>, <code>Blood Type</code>).</li>
<li><strong>Relationships (The Verbs):</strong> How they interact (e.g., <code>Doctor</code> <em>prescribes</em> <code>Drug</code>).</li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="summary-comparison" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary-comparison">Summary Comparison</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Feature</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Philosophical Ontology</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Computational Ontology</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Focus</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">The nature of reality.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">The structure of a specific domain’s data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Goal</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Truth and wisdom.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Interoperability (systems talking to each other).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Output</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Theories and essays.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Knowledge Graphs, code (OWL/RDF), databases.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Example</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“Is the mind separate from the body?”</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“A <code>Smartphone</code> <strong>is-a</strong> <code>Device</code>.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="why-is-this-important-right-now" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-is-this-important-right-now">Why is this important right now?</h3>
<p>You likely interact with ontologies every day without realizing it: * <strong>Google Search:</strong> When you search for “Jaguar,” Google uses an ontology to figure out if you mean the <strong>animal</strong>, the <strong>car</strong>, or the <strong>football team</strong> based on the other words in your query. * <strong>Healthcare:</strong> Ontologies allow different hospitals to share records. One system might say “Heart Attack” and another “Myocardial Infarction,” but the ontology links them as the exact same concept.</p>
</section>
<section id="commentary-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="commentary-1">Commentary</h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Prompt:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>That is much better. The notes or links for the elements of the response are and remain the problem; I would like them included in the document / markdown syntax that you provided so that they may be followed for more detailed inquiry.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="what-is-ontology" class="level1">
<h1>What is Ontology?</h1>
<p><strong>Ontology</strong> is, at its core, the study of <strong>what exists</strong> and <strong>how things are related</strong>.</p>
<p>Depending on whether you are talking to a philosopher or a computer scientist, the definition shifts from abstract reality to practical data structures.</p>
<p>Here is the breakdown of the two main perspectives:</p>
<section id="in-philosophy-the-origin-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-philosophy-the-origin-1">1. In Philosophy (The Origin)</h3>
<p>In philosophy, ontology is the “study of being.” It is a branch of metaphysics that asks deep questions about the nature of reality. This tradition traces back to <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/aristotle-metaphysics/">Aristotle’s Metaphysics</a> and continues in modern analytic philosophy.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Goal:</strong> To discover the fundamental categories of existence.</li>
<li><strong>Key Questions:</strong> What does it mean “to exist”? Do abstract ideas (like the number 7 or “justice”) exist in the same way a rock exists? This is often referred to as <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ontological-commitment/">Ontological Commitment</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> A philosopher might analyze if “holes” are real things, or if they are just the absence of something else.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="in-computer-science-the-application-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-computer-science-the-application-1">2. In Computer Science (The Application)</h3>
<p>In computer science (specifically AI and Information Science), an ontology is a <strong>formal blueprint</strong> used to model knowledge. It is a specific way of organizing data so that computers can “understand” it.</p>
<p>The most widely cited definition comes from <strong>Tom Gruber</strong>, who defined an ontology as a <a href="https://tomgruber.org/writing/ontology-definition-2007.htm">“formal, explicit specification of a shared conceptualization”</a>.</p>
<p>Instead of asking “what is reality,” a computational ontology declares: <em>“For this specific system, these are the only things that exist, and here is how they connect.”</em></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Goal:</strong> To help software share data, reason about information, and avoid confusion (Interoperability).</li>
<li><strong>The “Triples” Structure:</strong> Most computational ontologies (like those built with the <a href="https://www.w3.org/OWL/">W3C Web Ontology Language (OWL)</a>) are built on three main components:
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Classes (The Nouns):</strong> The categories of things (e.g., <code>Patient</code>, <code>Doctor</code>, <code>Drug</code>).</li>
<li><strong>Attributes (The Adjectives):</strong> The properties of those things (e.g., <code>Name</code>, <code>Dosage</code>, <code>Blood Type</code>).</li>
<li><strong>Relationships (The Verbs):</strong> How they interact (e.g., <code>Doctor</code> <em>prescribes</em> <code>Drug</code>).</li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="summary-comparison-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary-comparison-1">Summary Comparison</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Feature</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Philosophical Ontology</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Computational Ontology</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Focus</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">The nature of reality.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">The structure of a specific domain’s data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Goal</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Truth and wisdom.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Interoperability (systems talking to each other).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Output</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Theories and essays.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Knowledge Graphs, code (OWL/RDF), databases.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Example</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“Is the mind separate from the body?”</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“A <code>Smartphone</code> <strong>is-a</strong> <code>Device</code>.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="why-is-this-important-right-now-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-is-this-important-right-now-1">Why is this important right now?</h3>
<p>You likely interact with ontologies every day without realizing it: * <strong>Google Search:</strong> When you search for “Jaguar,” Google uses a <a href="https://blog.google/products/search/about-knowledge-graph/">Knowledge Graph</a> (an ontology) to figure out if you mean the <strong>animal</strong>, the <strong>car</strong>, or the <strong>football team</strong>. * <strong>Healthcare:</strong> Ontologies allow different hospitals to share records. One system might say “Heart Attack” and another “Myocardial Infarction,” but the ontology links them as the exact same concept (see <a href="https://www.snomed.org/">SNOMED CT</a>).</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="references-further-reading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references-further-reading">References &amp; Further Reading</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Philosophy:</strong> Hofweber, T. (2020). <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/logic-ontology/">“Logic and Ontology”</a>. <em>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</em>.</li>
<li><strong>Computer Science:</strong> Gruber, T. (1993). <a href="https://tomgruber.org/writing/ontology-definition-2007.htm">“What is an Ontology?”</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Standards:</strong> World Wide Web Consortium (W3C). <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/">“OWL 2 Web Ontology Language Document Overview”</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Comparison:</strong> Smith, B. (2003). <a href="http://ontology.buffalo.edu/smith/articles/ontologies.htm">“Ontology: Philosophical and Computational”</a>.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Gemini-Formatting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Gemini-Formatting/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="73" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lesson Learned on Gemini</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert W. Walker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Lesson-Learned/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./ModelsData.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Of Note"><img src="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Lesson-Learned/ModelsData.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Of Note"></a></p>
<figcaption>Of Note</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="tldr" class="level1">
<h1>TL;DR</h1>
<p>Gemini is powerful, and a few tidbits help a great deal. I use <code>markdown</code> formatting for text inputs and Gemini is well versed in this. My prompts now use <code>please format responses in markdown and include links to the noted sources</code>.</p>
</section>
<section id="getting-formatted-responses-from-gemini-the-first-time" class="level1">
<h1>Getting Formatted Responses from Gemini the First Time</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Prompt:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Please take the following link: <code>https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/</code> and rewrite the document for me at an early high school level. The response should formatted with references in markdown code.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="models-in-science" class="level1">
<h1>Models in Science</h1>
<p><strong>Source:</strong> <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Models in Science</a></p>
<p>In science, models are some of the most important tools researchers use. You might have seen the “billiard ball model” of a gas in chemistry or the “double helix” model of DNA in biology. Scientists spend a lot of time building, testing, and fixing these models.</p>
<p>But what exactly is a model? Philosophers of science have thought a lot about this. This article explores what models are, how they represent the world, and how we learn from them.</p>
<section id="how-models-represent-the-world" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-models-represent-the-world">1. How Models Represent the World</h2>
<p>Models are like maps or pictures—they represent something else. Philosophers usually divide them into two main types based on what they represent.</p>
<section id="models-of-phenomena" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="models-of-phenomena">Models of Phenomena</h3>
<p>These are models of things or events in the real world. * <strong>Examples:</strong> The Bohr model of the atom, a scale model of a bridge, or a computer model of the weather. * <strong>The Big Question:</strong> How does a model (which is just an object or an idea) represent a real phenomenon? It’s similar to asking how a painting represents a landscape.</p>
</section>
<section id="models-of-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="models-of-data">Models of Data</h3>
<p>Scientific data often comes from observations that are “messy.” There might be errors or irrelevant details. * <strong>What they do:</strong> A “model of data” is a cleaned-up version of that information. * <strong>Example:</strong> If you plot points on a graph and they are scattered, you might draw a smooth curve through them. That smooth curve is the <em>model</em> of the data. It helps scientists see the pattern rather than just the noise.</p>
</section>
<section id="different-styles-of-models" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="different-styles-of-models">Different Styles of Models</h3>
<p>Scientists use different styles to represent things, just like artists use different styles (like realism or abstract art).</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scale Models:</strong> These are just smaller (or larger) physical copies of the target.
<ul>
<li><em>Example:</em> A wooden model of a car or a plastic model of a DNA molecule. They look like the real thing but might be made of different materials.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Idealized Models:</strong> These models simplify reality to make it easier to understand.
<ul>
<li><strong>“Stripping Away” (Aristotelian):</strong> You ignore details that don’t matter for your problem. For example, when studying planetary orbits, you might treat a planet as a simple dot with mass, ignoring its mountains and oceans.</li>
<li><strong>“Distorting” (Galilean):</strong> You imagine a world that physically cannot exist to test a theory. For example, imagining a surface with <em>zero friction</em> or a market where everyone knows <em>everything</em>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Analogical Models:</strong> These use a familiar object to explain something new.
<ul>
<li><em>Example:</em> Describing the nucleus of an atom as a “liquid drop.” It isn’t actually a drop of liquid, but it behaves like one in some ways.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="what-are-models-made-of-ontology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-models-made-of-ontology">2. What Are Models Made Of? (Ontology)</h2>
<p>If you hold a model car, it’s made of wood or plastic. But what is a <em>scientific</em> model made of?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Physical Objects:</strong> Some are real material things, like the model of a bridge used in a wind tunnel.</li>
<li><strong>Fictional Objects:</strong> Some philosophers argue that models are like characters in a book (like Sherlock Holmes). They don’t exist in the real world, but we can still study them and learn true things about them.</li>
<li><strong>Math and Sets:</strong> Many scientists view models as mathematical structures (sets of equations and rules).</li>
<li><strong>Descriptions:</strong> Some simply say a model is just a detailed description of a system.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="learning-with-models-epistemology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-with-models-epistemology">3. Learning with Models (Epistemology)</h2>
<p>We use models because we can’t always test the real world. We can’t easily crash real trains to test safety, so we use models. Learning happens in two steps:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Learning <em>about</em> the Model:</strong> We run experiments or simulations on the model itself. For example, we might run a computer program to see how a digital disease spreads.</li>
<li><strong>Translating to Reality:</strong> We take what we learned from the model and apply it to the real world. If the model bridge collapses in the wind tunnel, we assume the real bridge might collapse in a real storm.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="models-vs.-theories" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="models-vs.-theories">4. Models vs.&nbsp;Theories</h2>
<p>Is a model the same thing as a theory? It’s a bit fuzzy, but here are two main views:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Syntactic View:</strong> This is an older view that focuses on logic. It says a “theory” is a set of sentences or math equations, and a “model” is just a way to interpret those equations.</li>
<li><strong>The Semantic View:</strong> This is the more modern view. It says that the <em>theory</em> is actually a collection of models. For example, “Classical Mechanics” isn’t just a list of rules; it’s the family of all the different models (pendulums, planetary orbits, billiard balls) that follow those rules.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">5. Conclusion</h2>
<p>Models are central to how modern science works. They are not just side-projects; they are the main instruments scientists use to represent the world, manipulate data, and formulate theories. Whether they are physical objects, complex equations, or imagined fictions, models help us grasp the complexity of the universe.</p>
<hr>
<section id="references-further-reading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references-further-reading">References &amp; Further Reading</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Original Article:</strong> Frigg, Roman and Hartmann, Stephan, <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/">“Models in Science”</a>, <em>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</em> (Fall 2013 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.).</li>
<li><strong>Reference on Representation:</strong> <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/#Bib">Van Fraassen, B. C. (1980). <em>The Scientific Image</em>. Oxford: Clarendon.</a></li>
<li><strong>Reference on Data Models:</strong> <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/#Bib">Suppes, P. (1962). “Models of Data”.</a></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Lesson-Learned/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/Lesson-Learned/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="73" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Syllabus and Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert W. Walker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-13-2026/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What is a model?</p>
<p>Our reading for next time defines models in science. This is a hard read but it is the only reading for the week.</p>
<p><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2013/entries/models-science/">Models in Science from the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</a></p>
<p>We will pay extra attention to sections 1, 3, and 5.2.</p>
<p>The class plan:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Discuss the syllabus, deliverables, and requirements</li>
<li>An overview of the course and mutual introductions.</li>
<li>A brief discussion of models to set the foundations for Thursday.</li>
</ol>
<p>Your assignment for next time:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Do the reading.</li>
<li>Collect at least three questions and the answers provided by Google Gemini about references in the reading that were unfamiliar. If you did not run across at least three unfamiliar references, you need a more advanced course.</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-13-2026/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/01-13-2026/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To BUS 1301: Managing with AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert W. Walker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<marquee scrollamount="10">
<h1>
<p style="color:purple;">
<i class="fa-brands fa-r-project" aria-label="r-project"></i>obertwwalker.github.io <br>
</p>
</h1>
<p></p></marquee><p></p>
<p>Welcome to Managing with Data, Analytics, and Artificial Intelligence!</p>
<section id="our-goal-in-four-parts" class="level1">
<h1>Our Goal in Four Parts</h1>
<p>Together, we will investigate how managers collect, process, and interpret observations about the world around them to facilitate informed decisions.</p>
<section id="models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="models">1. Models</h2>
<ul>
<li>Our organizing framework is the <em>model</em>. What is a model? Why models?</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data">2. Data</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>What is data and how do we get some? We start by defining data and our relationship with data. We will explore practical methods of data gathering – from surveys and archives to experiments and crowd sourcing.</p></li>
<li><p>Have data, how is it typically organized? We will explore basic methods of organizing data for robust, sustainable use.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="deploying-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deploying-data">3. Deploying Data</h2>
<ul>
<li>How can managers use data? We will deploy basic tools of cross tabulation, frequency distributions, and simple plots before some statistical inference and model building.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="artificial-intelligence" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="artificial-intelligence">4. Artificial Intelligence</h2>
<ul>
<li>What is artificial intelligence (AI)? We will highlight general features of how commonly deployed AI systems function and how they can solve challenges across various areas of business.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="learning-objectives" class="level1">
<h1>Learning Objectives</h1>
<p>Our key learning objectives, for the course, are:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>What is a model? What role do models play in the origination of data [for empiricists]?</li>
<li>Distinguish among means of data collection and discuss their tradeoffs.<br>
</li>
<li>Describe common models of data management and their tradeoffs.<br>
</li>
<li>Articulate the applicability of popular analytic techniques to their uses and their function.<br>
</li>
<li>Discuss the historical development and current functionality of <em>AI</em>.<br>
</li>
<li>Ethical issues are ubiquitous in data, analytics, and AI in the workplace; we should confront them.</li>
</ol>
<p>Our week 1 learning objective is to define a model, give examples of models and their use in management activities, and the interrelationship between models and measures, a lead-in to specifics on data.</p>
</section>
<section id="core-tools" class="level1">
<h1>Core Tools</h1>
<p>We will make extensive use of a few software and computing tools.</p>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Word and Microsoft Excel [licenses provided via Willamette if needed]</li>
<li>Google Docs and Sheets</li>
<li><a href="https://gemini.google.com/">Google Gemini</a>, in lieu of a subscription to OpenAI, Anthropic, or similar</li>
<li><a href="https://notebooklm.google.com/">NotebookLM</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="readings" class="level1">
<h1>Readings</h1>
<p>A free and open-source textbook will provide background and exercises in the generic field of statistics.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openintro.org/book/os/">Open Intro Statistics</a>. The .pdf file is available on canvas and a screen reader version can be obtained from the link.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://robertwwalker.github.io/BUS1301-SP26/posts/welcome/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
